Finding Aid for Isaac M. Weston Papers 1859-1899
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Isaac M. Weston Papers 1859-1899
Weston, Isaac M. (Isaac Mellen), 1845-1898.
3 oversize volumes
6 linear feet
Grand Rapids Michigan businessman and politician, active in lumbering and banking in Wisconsin and Michigan, Democratic party official, head of Board of World's Fair Managers for Michigan, overseeing state's exhibits at 1893 Columbian Exposition. Collection primarily documents business activities with some material on World's Columbian Exposition, as well as personal and family material.
85526 Aa/2, AC
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Miss Nancy Weston. The principal accession came to the library in 1979. (Donor no. 5552 )
The collection is open for research.
Isaac Mellen Weston was born April 20, 1845 in North Anson, Maine. The chronology of his life from those years in Maine until he established permanent residency in Michigan in 1867 gives the impression of a youth both restless and enterprising. He moved with his family to Milwaukee, Wisconsin in 1857. In 1862, he participated in the Little Crow Indian Campaign serving as a lieutenant with a Minnesota regiment. From 1863 to 1865, he attended the University of Michigan. From there, he was for a time a traveling correspondent for the Chicago Times. Later in 1865, he worked as military storekeeper at Fort Laramie, Dakota Territory. And, in 1866, he was managing editor of the Daily Union Vedette in Salt Lake City, Utah, an anti-Mormon, anti-Brigham Young newspaper.
About this time, Weston's life took on greater permanence. In 1867, he became an associate with his father William Weston in the manufacture of lumber in Wisconsin and in Whitehall, a lumbering city, located in Muskegon County, Michigan. In 1877, he became cashier and manager of the First National Bank of Whitehall where his father was then president. Following the retirement of his father in 1879, Weston became the president of the bank. He later moved to Grand Rapids in 1881 where he worked as cashier of the Farmers and Mechanics Bank which he reorganized as the Fourth National Bank.
Around this time too, Weston involved himself in local and state politics. In 1880, he was nominated for the office of state treasurer. He was treasurer of the Grand Rapids Board of Education from 1881 to 1883. He also served as a member of the Grand Rapids Board of Police and Fire Commissioners. And in 1888, he was elected mayor of the city on the Democratic ticket. Weston was an influential member of the state's Democratic structure. He was a member of the state executive committee for six years, party treasurer for four years, and party chairman also for four years. In 1888, Weston was elected as the first delegate-at-large from Michigan to attend the Democratic National Convention to be held in St. Louis, Missouri. The nominee of this convention, Grover Cleveland, later appointed Weston to be a government commissioner with responsibility to examine, for acceptance, the portion of the Southern Pacific Railroad between San Francisco and Portland, Oregon.
In 1893, Weston was president of the Board of World's Fair Managers for Michigan. In this capacity, Weston had the responsibility for approving and overseeing all of the exhibits from Michigan to be displayed at the Columbian Exposition.
Up until the time of his death, Weston led a full and varied life. He was president of a political organization known as the Association of the Northwest. In 1890, he helped to purchase and manage the Grand Rapids Democrat, one of the city's newspapers. He was a member of the Peninsular Club, member and president of O-Wash-Ta-Nong Boat Club, and member resident of the Detroit Club. Weston never married. He died December 10, 1898 in New York City and is buried in North Anson, Maine.
The Weston collection primarily documents the career of Isaac M. Weston. Included are smaller series of papers of his brother and father. The collection includes correspondence, topical files, business and legal papers, and photographs. Of note are materials concerning Michigan's exhibit at the World Fair in 1893 and papers concerning lumbering and land interests in Michigan and Wisconsin.
Subjects:
Democratic Party (Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Lumbering--Wisconsin.; Lumbering--Michigan.; Michigan Board of World's Fair Managers.; Michigan--Politics and government--1877-1898.; American newspapers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.); Logging--Michigan.; Logging--Wisconsin.; Weston, Isaac M. (Isaac Mellen), 1845-1898.; Wisconsin.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Clubhouses--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Clubs.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Clubhouses.; Grand River (Mich.); Lumber industry.; O-Wash-ta-Nong Boat Club.; Sailboats.; Weston, Isaac M. (Isaac Mellen), 1845-1898.
Contributors:
Weston, B. F. (Benjamin Frank), d. 1916.; Weston, William, 1810-1882.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- I. M. Weston
  The Isaac M. Weston portion of the collection consists of three subseries of papers documenting the business and political career of I.M. Weston. 1. Correspondence, 1859-1899, concerning business and personal interests, and containing papers relating to his association with the World's Columbian Exposition in 1893; 2. Topical files, ca. 1870-1898, relating to business and financial affairs, the Columbian Exposition, and legal matters; and 3. Business records, 1862-1895, consisting of bound ledgers and accounts, files of property transactions (largely unsorted), and personal bound records, including personal scrapbooks and scrapbooks relating to the 1893 Exposition.
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1859-1866 (Box 1)
    - 1867-1868 (Box 1)
    - 1869 (Box 1)
    - 1870-1871 (Box 1)
    - 1872-1879 (Box 1)
    - Undated, 1880-1883 (Box 1)
    - 1884-1886 (Box 1)
    - 1887 (Box 1)
    - 1888 (Box 1)
    - 1889 (Box 1)
    - Undated, January-April 1890 (Box 1)
    - May-August 1890 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1890 (Box 1)
    - 1891 (Box 1)
    - 1892 (Box 1)
    - Undated 1893-1894 (Box 1)
    - 1893 (Box 1)
    - 1894 (Box 1)
    - 1895 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1896 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1896 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1897 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1897 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1898 (Box 1)
    - May-August 1898 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1898 (Box 1)
    - 1899 (Box 1)
  - Topical file circa 1870-1898
    - Addresses and speeches (Box 1)
    - American Missionary Associations Arctic Station (Box 1)
    - Engine at Hustmouth Iron Works, Big Rapids, Mich. (Box 1)
    - Liberal Arts (Box 1)
      includes information, correspondence to schools, performing artists, etc.
    - Lumbering notes (Box 1)
    - Michigan Bell Telephone Company suit 1890 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    - Telegrams 1887-1898 (Box 1)
    - Utah matter--Mormon information and land deeds (Box 1)
    - Weston family
      - Marianne Weston Will 1898 (Box 1)
      - William Weston miscellaneous deeds and mortgages (Box 1)
    - World's Columbian Exposition 1893
      - Commissioner's dinner (Box 1)
      - Dedication of Michigan Building October 1892 (Box 1)
        includes Michigan Days, 1893
      - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
        (see also correspondence)
      - Honey Exhibit (Box 1)
      - Michigan introduction to the fair exhibit (Box 1)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Business records 1862-1895
    - Account book, Mayor (?) John J. Belknap expenses 1881 (Box 2)
    - Business expense record books
      - "Daybook" 1880-1890 (Box 2)
      - "Journal" 1890-1891 (Box 2)
    - Land Ledgers, city of Grand Rapids-land addition from Weston and Low 1889-1890 (Box 2)
      2 volumes
    - Land record books
      - 1883 (Box 2)
      - 1892-1895 (Box 2)
    - Lumber and log price book 1882 edition (Box 2)
    - Mortgage register 1888-1892 (Box 2)
    - Trial balance book 1887-1892 (Volume 1)
    - Weston and Meigs Journal 1888-1890 (Volume 2)
    - Miscellaneous land deeds, shipping documents, business articles, and other papers related to business activities (Box 2)
    - Subject business records
      in brown case files
      - Building (corner of Fulton and Calder Streets) (Box 3)
      - Dreage Company (Box 3)
      - Grand Rapids Hydraulics (Box 3)
      - Leases (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous 1879 and previous (Box 3)
      - Unmarked
        - Deeds, receipts, etc. circa 1889-1892 (Box 3)
        - Land files
          - Champlin, J.W. (trustee) (Box 3)
          - Clay, D.P. (Box 3)
          - Craw, E.L. matter of (Box 3)
          - Featherly, David (Box 3)
          - First National Bank, Cheybogan (Box 3)
          - Grand Rapids Telegraph Co. papers (Box 3)
          - Kingsmouth, Ellen (Box 3)
          - Lathrop, George (Detroit attorney) (Box 3)
          - Mather, Samuel (Box 3)
          - Weston, Marianne S. (Box 3)
        - Tax receipts circa 1892 (Box 3)
      - West Leon St. Property (north front) (Box 3)
      - Weston and Meigs
        - Property (Box 3)
        - Securities (Box 3)
      - Weston, C.E. (Box 3)
        (deeds, patents, tax receipts, etc.)
    - Miscellaneous packets relating to business and land associates
      - Fourth National Bank (Box 3)
      - Grand Rapids Fire Insurance (Box 3)
      - Gould, William (land) (Box 3)
      - Hathaway, William (Box 3)
      - Lacry, James D. (Box 3)
      - McGarry (Box 3)
      - Martin lands (Box 3)
      - Mauer, Anna M. (lands) (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Stocks (Box 3)
        - Tax receipts 1862-1892 (Box 3)
      - North Republic Mining Company (Box 3)
      - Sliding Railway papers (Box 3)
      - Standard Life Insurance Company (Box 3)
      - Street Railway Company (Box 3)
      - Township maps, Weston lands (Box 3)
      - Weston and Meigs (lot no. 63) (Box 3)
      - Weston and Watson (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous court cases and legal agreements (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous business material
      - Balance sheets (Box 4)
      - Financial statements (Box 4)
      - Land contracts and abstracts (Box 4)
      - Mortgages (Box 4)
      - Receipts (Box 4)
      - Warranty and claim deeds (Box 4)
  - Personal records 1865-1899
    - Autograph book 1865-1869 (Box 5)
    - Detroit Club booklet (Box 5)
    - Newspaper scrapbooks
      - Democratic State Committee (Box 5)
      - Personal career
        - 1876 (Box 5)
        - 1884-1886 (Box 5)
        - 1886-1887 (Box 5)
        - 1894-1895 (Box 5)
        - 1895-1897 (Box 5)
      - World's Fair, State of Michigan (Box 5)
      - Scrapbook concerning Michigan Board of World's Fair Managers 1893 (Volume 3)
    - "Report of the World's Fair Managers for the State of Michigan, " I.M. Weston, editor 1899 (Box 5)
- B.F. Weston
  The B. F. Weston series concerns I.M. Weston's brother and includes financial files, 1859-1866, and other business records, 1880-1901. The B.F. Weston series largely concerns his lumbering investments.
  - Financial files 1859-1866
    - Unknown (Box 6)
      - Undated (Box 6)
      - 1862 (Box 6)
      - 1866 (Box 6)
    - Cleveland
      - 1861, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1862 (Box 6)
    - Milwaukee
      - 1859 (Box 6)
      - 1859-1866 (Box 6)
    - Riverdale Farm 1860 (Box 6)
  - Other business material 1880-1884, 1897-1901
    - Financial Journal (lumber company at Whitehall, Mich.) 1880-1884 (Box 6)
    - Ledgers, Shanty Book Lumber Camp (near Allayton, Mich.)
      - 1880 (Box 6)
      - 1882 (Box 6)
    - Scale book (for logging) 1881 (Box 6)
    - Tenant register (for Grand Rapids building) 1897-1901 (Box 6)
    - Time book (lumber co.) 1882 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous deeds, mortgages, land contracts, etc. relating mostly to lumbering interests, 1 folders (Box 6)
- William Weston
  William Weston was the father of the two Weston brothers. This small series consists of one packet of patents for the period, 1866-1869.
  - U.S. Patents 1866-1869 [one packet] (Box 6)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists of portraits; photographs and drawing of O-Wash-ta-Nong Boat Club (Grand Rapids, Mich.) and group of Club officers; and photograph of timber hauled from the Upper Peninsula to the Chicago World's Fair (1893).
  - Various, 2 folders (Box 6)